Finding Aid for War of 1812 Collection
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- War of 1812 collection
  - 1815 January 12. Joseph S. Winter ALS to Elisha I. Winter; New Orleans, [Louisiana]., 4 pages; Describes the Battle of New Orleans; "never was there an action wherein one side suffered so much and the other so little we having lost but six men killed and nine wounded & the British lost at least 1500 killed wounded & prisoners…" Includes a breakdown of the British troops that are killed or imprisoned (wounded and unwounded).
  - 1815 January 18 to 1815 January 19. T. Searl ALS to Lucy Searl; Alexandria, [Virginia]., 3 pages; Recounts his various experiences with Virginians.
  - 1815 January 19. Caesar Augustus Rodney ALS to Thomas Macdonough; Senate Chamber, Dover, [Delaware]., 2 pages; Regarding Thomas Macdonough’s victory over the British fleet on Lake Champlain.
  - 1815 January 21. Thomas Hamilton ALS to Farish Carter; Camp 5 miles below Hartford, [Georgia]., 1 page; Delivery of rations to Hartford; "Circumstances make it necessary that you should immediately turn your attention to the delivery at Hartford of thirty thousand Complete Rations Contemplated in a requisition…and as I am ordered to operate within the Settled limits of Georgia you will take Such Steps...to keep the Detachment...constantly furnished with thirty thousand Rations."
  - 1815 January 24. U.S. Army Brigade under Coffee DS; Camp Coffee., 1 page; Report of the Brigade under John Coffee, signed by Joel Parrish Jr., "Brig Inspector."
  - 1815 January 30. Joseph Bradley Varnum LS to George Thacher; Washington., 32 pages; A U.S. Representative from Massachusetts and staunch supporter of the war, Varnum defends the Republicans [Democratic-Republicans] from Thacher's charges against them. Folder includes Lawrence Kaplan's 1964 “A New Englander Defends the War of 1812."
  - 1815 February 4. James Morrison ALS to Charles Simms; Washington., 2 pages; He is attempting to find transportation for the Kentucky Troops ordered to back-up Jackson’s Army. Discusses matters concerning his finances and his landlord receiving payment.
  - 1815 February 6. Garrigues de Flaujac ALS to Andrew Jackson; New Orleans, [Louisiana]., 2 pages; Regarding Garrigues brigade of militia (in French).
  - 1815 February 13. S[tephen] Chase ALS to Stephen Chase; Baltimore, Maryland., 5 page; Son's letter to his father, regarding previously requested advice on a commission in the army. Discussion of Maryland troops and business in Baltimore versus that in Maryland. Celebrations in Baltimore in response to news of peace.; Original located in the Duane Norman Diedrich Collection.
  - 1815 February 23. James G. Almy ALS to John C. Almy; Savannah, [Georgia]., 3 pages; Regarding preparations to defend Savannah; moving women, children, books, and papers out of harm's way. Almy states that he has been in poor health, but that he would have been ready to fight, except for the news of "peace since Cockburn took St. Mary's". He further notes that the loss of "a large slave population and fear of a general insurrection has caused us a great solicitude and anxiety - upwards of 600 prime slaves have been taken off by those ruffians, and enormities committed that would disgrace Cossacks or barbarians."
  - 1815 March 2. Martha Shackelford ALS to Abby P. Manning; George Town, [South Carolina]., 3 pages; Thanks to God for the end of the war; "as the blessing of Peace is once more restored to our Happy Land…may we be a Grateful people and know how to appreciate its Value…" Describes the celebration, includes lines from the hymn Thanksgiving for Victory Over Our Enemies.
  - 1815 March 8. Thomas Nicholls ADS; New Orleans, Louisiana., 2 pages; Statement concerning the worth of Major David Abbot’s horse, which was killed in battle by a cannon ball; it was worth $150. Abbot served with the 3rd Regiment of Tennessee Militia.
  - 1815 March 6. J.L.C. Hardy ALS to William Moultrie Reid; New Orleans, [Louisiana]., 3 pages; Regarding a skirmish fought after the Battle of New Orleans; "I have now to inform you of a very narrow Escape I had of being made a prisoner by the English…"Of the battle, "they had to lament the loss of two of their first Generals & other Officers & about 6,000 men - our whole loss was only about 200 or 300 men..."
  - 1815 March. Louisa C. Shaw ALS to Sir George Cockburn; Cumberland Island, [Georgia]., 2 pages; Letter of thanks and goodwill.
  - [ca. 1815 March]. AMs; s.l., 2 pages; List of sixteen "Prisoners," deserters from the U.S. Army, coming from six different infantry and two artillery units. Lists names, charges, promises for good behavior and payment of costs, and occasionally notes the reasons for desertion and punishments. Names of deserters include: Solomon Avery, Luther Brooks, Levi Cass, William Granger, William Hall, David Heath, Moses Heath, Samuel Hilton, Johnson Lovering, William McIntire, Moses Meeder, Samuel Merrick, William Miles, William Rines, Samuel Tibbets, and David Tucker. Reasons for desertion include family and personal illness, financial distress, following the "advice of his Father, being under age," and ignorance of the law.
  - 1815 April 5. Caesar Augustus Rodney, Jesse Green, and Cornelius F. Comegys LS to [Thomas Macdonough]; Dover, [Delaware]., 4 pages; Enclosing resolution of the Senate and House of Delaware concerning Macdonough’s victory on Lake Champlain, "expressing, on their behalf, their sentiments & feelings, on the subject of your late engagement, with a superior fleet of the enemy, on Lake Champlain." Folder include two page resolution dated February 10, 1815 from the Delaware House and Senate.
  - 1815 April 5. John Thomas DS to John Newman; Natchez, [Mississippi]., 2 pages; Addressed to Maj. Genl. Andrew Jackson, an order for two dollars to be paid to Newman. Includes receipt on the back stating that Col. John Davies delivered the money.
  - 1815 April 16.. H[unter], M.A. ALS to George W. Hunter; New Orleans, [Louisiana]., 3 pages; News in New Orleans; "I was going to congratulate your mother upon the Peace, but the news of it was so soon followed by that of the war with Algiers, that I could not have that pleasure." Offers encouragement should Hunter be sent there. They arrives just as Jackson was departing; "he is almost idolised here particularly by the ladies..."
  - 1815 April 17. Edmund Pendleton Gaines ALS to James Taylor; New Orleans, [Louisiana]., 2 pages; Regarding the Battle of New Orleans; "the place has been saved, the British Army covered with everlasing Shame, and ours with imperishable glory - General Jackson's name is immortalized - peace is restored."
  - 1815 June 13. [James] Hall ALS to Thomas I. Wharton; Boston, [Massachusetts]., 3 pages; Discusses Bostonians' lack of regard for officers; "I am heartily sick of Boston…The people here look upon officers with disgust and terror - No gentleman who has a virgin daughter invites one willingly to his house - They seem to think we will exercise the right of Search upon all female bottoms..." Mentions being present at Governor [Caleb] Strong's induction into office.
  - [post 1815 October]. U.S. Army. Document., 1 page; Memo respecting Sergeant Gardiner’s appeal; the Captain General had been authorized to discharge commanding officers and sergeants "and to delegate this power to such subordinate Officers as he might think proper…The Act passed in [October] 1815 gave no such right of delegation respecting Sergeants..."
  - 1815 November 20. James McCloskey ALS to [William Harris Crawford]; Quarter Master General’s Department, Detroit, [Michigan]., 2 pages; Addressed to the Secretary of War, concerns an unpaid bill of $358 for beef cattle.
  - 1815 December 15. Andrew Jackson ALS to William H. Crawford; Washington, [D.C.]., 3 pages; Concerning staff organization of the army; "I conceive it a medical defect in the Act for the organization of the peace establishment that most of the important branches of the Staff have been left without a Head…I would therefore recommend as a measure of primary consequence that such officers as have been provisionally retained by retained permanently." Folder includes two-page manuscript schedule of stationary staff and division staff.
  - 1815. 4 Documents., 4 pages; Receipts.
  - [1815 ca.]. [British Army, 100th Regiment of Foot] Pr. DS to John Guthrey., 1 page; Certifies that Guthrey, under Lieut. Col. Pilkington, was present at the capture of Moose Island, [Maine]. He "is entitled to any Emoluments arising from said Capture."
  - 1816 March 7. James Monroe ALS to John Mason; Washington., 1 page; Regarding impressment and start of war; he recounts communication with Beasley during the war "stating that our impressed seamen had been delivered over, from differing frigates, to rescue them from the…fighters against their country, & [lodged] in prison." Many of them were imprisoned in Dartmoor, and the British government had demanded their release.
  - 1818 August 11. F.W. Armstrong ALS; Knoxville, Tennessee., 1 page; Record of Armstrong’s promotion through the army. "Shortly After the Attack on the Chesepeak" he became lieutenant in a volunteer company, a captain in the infantry, and appointed Brigade Inspector.
  - 1818 September 21. E. Mattoon Pr. DS to Zenas Stebbins; Boston, Massachusetts., 1 page; The Governor of Massachusetts [John Brooks] has accepted Stebbins' resignation as lieutenant colonel commanded and colonel by brevet of the 1st Artillery Brigade in the 4th Division of the Massachusetts Militia. He has been honorably discharged.
  - 1818 November 16. Charles Colerick DS; United States., 3 pages; Regarding three months extra pay due to Colerick, a volunteer marine, for services in the Battle of Lake Erie. He served under the command of James Coburn; "I have never received any part of the extra pay…" Includes a two-page deposition by John Payne regarding Colerick, dated November 16, 1818. Payne was a captain of a troop of volunteer dragoons detached from the Kentucky militia.
  - 1818 December 18. John Clement ALS to Peter Hagner; Haddenfield [New Jersey]., 2 pages; Clement seeks pay for his time as paymaster in the war; he incloses letters regarding power of attorney.
  - 1819 January 14. John Clement ALS to Peter Hagner; Haddenfield, [New Jersey]., 5 pages; Clement’s seeking pay for his time as paymaster in war; he has received Hagner's letter stating that his accounts had beene examined and there "there was a balance due..of $1742.19, differing from my own statement to that Amount, with and enclosed statement shewing me how the difference had arisen, requesting me to Remove the objections to the Suspended Items made in my Account."
  - 1819 January 28. John Clement ALS to Peter Hagner; Haddenfield, [New Jersey]., 2 pages; Clement’s seeking pay for his time as paymaster in war; he gives an account of his services, beginning with Madison's 1814 request of New Jersey for five thousand men.
  - 1819 February 5. John Clement ALS to Joseph Bloomfield; Haddenfield, [New Jersey]., 3 pages; Regarding Clement’s time as paymaster and issues surrounding it.
  - 1819 February 10. John Clement ALS to Joseph Bloomfield; Haddenfield, [New Jersey]., 2 pages; Clement seeks pay for his time as paymaster in war.
  - 1822 February 13. Robert Herriot Barclay ALS to John James Douglas., 6 pages; Barclay has been considering making an application for promotion to the Duke of Buckingham, as it relates to Buckingham's speech before the House of Lords about "my defeat upon Lake Erie." Folder includes a copy of Barclay's court martial, dated September 9, 1814, and Sir George Prevost's extract of general orders relating to Barclay’s conduct on Lake Erie. Also includes a private ALS from Barclay to Douglas dated May 22, 1822.
  - 1825 August 7. Sir George Cockburn ACyS to Louisa C. Shaw., 4 pages; Regarding payment, supplies, and forces under his command at Cumberland Island [Georgia]; "Gt. Britain was at the time at War with America, & Cumberland Island was taken by Force of Arms, you & your Possessions on the Island fell into our Hands, but as Individuals not carrying Arms you were respected &...orders were given not to injure your property nor to take anything belonging to you without paying for it..."
  - 1826 November 17. James Monroe ALS to W[illia]m F. Thornton., 2 pages; In this letter, recently retired U.S. President Monroe requests that Captain William F. Thornton recount, in writing, details related to the reconnaissance efforts used to monitor the British following their landing at Benedict, Maryland, August 1814.
  - 1831 November 16. Louis McLane DS; Treasury Department, Washington, [D.C.]., 3 pages; McLane, Secretary of the Treasury, settling account of James Taylor, Quarter Master General of the Northwest Army during the war. Countersigned by Thomas L. Smith, Register of the Treasury. Includes Taylor's account from 1812.
  - 1833 October 26. Jesse Duncan Elliott ALS to Samuel Smith; Navy Yard, Boston, [Massachusetts]., 1 page; Sending a small portion of supplies "which I hope will prove acceptable and useful in your own advancing age…"
  - 1834 February 22. Michigan Legislative Council Pr. DS to United States Congress., 2 pages; Regarding claims of Michigan citizens for property lost, captured, or destroyed in the war; "there are many worthy citizens of the Territory of Michigan, who...suffered severe and heavy losses or property...during the late war; since...they have sought relief from the government of the United States in vain." Includes manuscript resolution, dated February 26, 1834, that a copy be transmitted to the President, Speaker of the House and the delegate in Congress from Michigan Territory.
  - 1835 April 22. Andrew Mauchalk ALS; Washington, [D.C.]., 4 pages; Regrets that someone else, Dr. Wren, has received an appointment and not the recipient's father. He is "totally unacquainted with the duties of the Office...and, decidedly, the most unpopular man in Natchez." Discusses friendship with President Jackson, who has a "certain junto" around him inspecting incoming letters and is presumably responsible for Jackson's not replying to his letters yet. Vilifies George Poindexter for his role in the Battle of New Orleans.
  - 1837 January 11. Daniel Turner LS to John Holmes; Newport, [Rhode Island]., 2 pages; Regarding service of Dr. Usher Parsons, his older brother, in the Battle of Lake Erie and the war; "his duties were…more important than those of any other medical officer on the Lake during the first year of the War, or until the fleet of Commodore Perry was ready to Sail."
  - 1837 February. Thomas Holdup Stevens LS to John Holmes; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., 3 pages; Regarding service of Dr. Usher Parsons, a friend of his, in the Battle of Lake Erie and the war; "I believe Dr. Parsons is the only commissioned officer who was in the Battle of Lake Erie, who has not received from his native State some testimonial of its approbation..."
  - 1840 July 23. Theodore ALS to Mary W. Cady; Suffield., 3 pages; Letterhead engraved with a medal entitled “Major General William H. Harrison / Resolution of Congress April 4, 1818. Battle of the Thames October 5, 1813.”
  - 1841 January 20. [George] Ray ALS to James D. Ray; Detroit, [Michigan]., 4 pages; Reflection on the massacre at River Raisin [Frenchtown], Michigan in January 1813, "famous from the fact of its having been the place of one of the [most] brutal massacres…ever disgraced…"
  - 1847 April 12. John Neal ACyS to William H. Winder; Portland, Maine., 2 pages; Concerning the military and law career of William Henry Winder.
  - 1853 June 1. S. Cole ALS to Hugh D. McLellan; s.l., 2 pages; Update on Samuel Libbey’s War of 1812 pension case. Libbey served in Captain George Bender’s Company of the 9th Infantry. Unable to find his records or any proof that his disability stemmed from his service.
  - 1858 June 26. Lewis Elliott ALS to Justice of the Peace; Hampden, Ohio., 2 pages; Seeking information on George King, who claims to have served in a company of volunteers; he "wants to obtain a land warrant he sais that he belonged to a Company of volunteers Commanded by Captain Blanchard…said King has made an application but his Claim is not Granted the name of Captain Blanchard not being found at Washington..."
  - 1858 December 16. James Buchanan DS to John Baptiste LaPoint; Washington, [D.C.]., 1 page; Deed of 80 acres of land for War of 1812 service granted to LaPoint, a private in the Michigan militia has been granted to George M. Dewey.; Located in Oversize Manuscripts.
  - 1859 December 10. James Buchanan partially printed DS to James McClellan, 1 page; "In pursuance of the Act of Congress, approved MARCH 3, 1855, entitled 'An Act in addition to certain Acts granting Bounty Land to certain Officers and Soldiers who have been engaged in the Military Service of the United States…" Granting 120 acres of land for sale at Sioux City, Iowa, to James McClellan, "Private, Captain Miller's Company, Pennsylvania Militia, War of 1812." Names Jane Doak as the assignee. Secretarial signature of James Buchanan. Signed J. B. Leonard, Secretary, and J. N. Grange, Recorder of the General Land Office. Includes an image of the American flag. Recorded at the O'Brien County, Iowa, Records office on November 10, 1886, for taxation purposes.
  - 1860 February 15. Stephen Champlin ALS to L.B. Chavalier; Buffalo, [New York]., 1 page; Regarding Chevalier’s painting of the Battle of Lake Erie; "I think the enclosed representation You sent me of the Squadron at the close of the Battle is perfect…I would like to submit it to Dr Parsons who I shall see either here or in Providence next Spring."
  - 1860 August 27. Stephen Champlin ALS to L.B. Chevalier; Buffalo, [New York]., 1 page; Regarding Chevalier’s painting of the Battle of Lake Erie; he answers Chevalier's question by stating that "The Queen Charlotte was a full rigged ship." He congratulates him on his progress with the painting and hopes to see him in September in Cleveland.
  - [Post 1860 August 27]. L.B. Chevalier ACy to Stephen Champlin., 1 page; Regarding a ship, Queen Charlotte, used in the War of 1812; Chevalier called upon "Capt Miles who raised the Detroit and Queen Charlotte and filled them out in 1836…The Queen Charlotte was a Brig and no mistake about it, as the partners and steps showed conclusively. The deck was quite good..."
  - 1860 August 29. Stephen Champlin ALS to L.B. Chevalier; Buffalo, [New York]., 1 page; Regarding Chevalier’s painting of the Battle of Lake Erie and in particular information regarding the ship, Queen Charlotte. He recounts his experience with the ship following the battle.
  - Undated, June 6. James Biddle ALS to [William Bainbridge]; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., 2 pages; Naval matters; trying to get command of a ship
  - Undated. William Duane ALS to Callender Irvine., 1 page; A friend has enquired to him on how to obtain 26 swords and a trumpet; Duane wishes to know how they could be obtained, if at all.
  - Undated. Document., 2 pages; List of names of soldiers from the District of Columbia who served in the War of 1812.
  - Undated. David Riddle ALS to John Lewis Thomson, 2 pages; Regarding the military service of Thomas and Samuel Riddle, both veterans of the war. Samuel served on the Northern frontier and Thomas served under General Hull. Riddle's younger brother, Abram, "was about to march for the frontier when he was killed by his horse falling on him he was a sergeant of a volunteer troop of Dragoons, in the state of Ohio..."
  - Undated. General Committee of Defense Account to Isaac Roberdeau; s.l., 1 page; Itemized statement of "expences of topographical engineers." Includes expenses for transportation, surveying, and other sundries.
  - Undated [after 1824 July]. [John Orde] Creighton ALS., 4 pages; Discusses life aboard a ship [Incomplete].
  - Undated, after 1871 February 14. Samuel V. Niles of Washington, D.C. Pr. DS., 2 pages; "War of 1812 Declaration of a Widow for Pension" incomplete.
  - Undated. J.P. Wheeler ALS to Zenas Stebbins., 1 page; Letter of thanks for "unexampled treatment."
  - Undated. AMs; s.l., 2 pages; "The Yankey Tars."Manuscript copy of a version of the folksong "The Constitution and the Guerriere."Reference to the War of 1812 naval battle between Captain James Richard Dacres (1788-1853) of the HMS Guerriere and Captain Isaac Hull (1773-1843) of the Constitution."Now Brittons you / be still since wee/ have given you your / fill and Boast no / more of Dacris your/ Grandy O / John Bull may boast/ his fill & the world/ say what they will / But the yankey tar/ for fighting are the/ Dandy O"